<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Cycles Rocks</title>
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://cycles.rocks/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-08T06:09:38.155Z</updated>
  <id>http://cycles.rocks/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Jeremy Hornberger</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Raleigh-Spirit</title>
    <link href="http://cycles.rocks/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/"/>
    <id>http://cycles.rocks/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/</id>
    <published>2017-02-07T21:02:23.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-08T06:09:38.155Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/01.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit">
<p>After finishing the restoration of the Motobecane I became excited to do another restoration. So, I ended up purchasing an old Raleigh Spirit off Craigslist for $40. I wasn’t sure if it was worth it or not but I decided the bike looked good enough and would be fun.</p>
<a id="more"></a> 
<img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/02.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit">
<p>So, over the next several months, I set out to restore it.  The paint wasn’t terrible so I thought I would just remove all the rust spots.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/03.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/04.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/05.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>I really liked the plate on the front.  Unfortunately, the method of removing rust discolored it.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/06.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/46.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>Rear mud guard and rack.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/07.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/50.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>Crank and cotter pin.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/08.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/39.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/30.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>The wheels and freewheel were bad. I put the wheels along with the frame in an oxalic acid bath to remove the rust. I had to trash the freewheel because I force removed it. I wasn’t willing to spend $20 for a special tool that should cost half that at most, and only be used once.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/09.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>For the chain guard, I ended up using vinegar and aluminum foil. It was rusted and scratched bad and the chrome was removed on a lot of it, but looked nice in the end considering the condition it was in.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/10.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/29.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>The wheel’s probably need to be replaced since the inside is so bad. I got the rust off but there is no more chrome protection on a lot of it and it was rusting inside the little holes.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/17.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/18.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/47.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>The rust on the handlebars removed very nicely.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/19.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/40.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>The brake levers came out nicely after some soaking in vinegar and polishing. I bought a new friction shifter off Amazon.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/20.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/21.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/44.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/45.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>The derailleur was in nice condition and still works great.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/22.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/48.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>The steerer tube and bearings were completely dried out.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/23.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/24.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/25.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>The bottom bracket was difficult to remove.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/27.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/28.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>Bottom bracket bearings.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/26.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>Seat tube and stem.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/31.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>The pedals came out nice after soaking and polishing.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/32.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<p>All the rust was removed from the frame after soaking in an oxalic acid bath for several days. I Wish I would have taken time to remove the decals but I didn’t know how or think about it.<br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/33.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/34.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/35.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/36.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"><br><img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/38.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit"></p>
<img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/41.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit">
<img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/42.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit">
<img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/43.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit">
<img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/49.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit">
<img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/51.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit">
<img src="/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/52.jpg" alt="Raleigh Spirit" title="Raleigh Spirit">
<p>After several months of research and careful planning, I finally finished the bike. I’ve ridden the bike several times to work and is very pleasant to ride, as long as the hills aren’t too steep.</p>
<p>Since the bike is only a 5 speed, it can be tough especially when pulling your kid in a trailer up a big hill with a 15 MPH wind against you. </p>
<p>I will say though, it made me proud when I passed others going up hills on my commutes to work. A bike like this you wouldn’t think is fast, but when your lowest gear is 28 teeth, and you are pushing a heavy steel bike up hills, it really works your calf muscles!</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;img src=&quot;/2017/02/07/Raleigh-Spirit/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raleigh Spirit&quot; title=&quot;Raleigh Spirit&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finishing the restoration of the Motobecane I became excited to do another restoration. So, I ended up purchasing an old Raleigh Spirit off Craigslist for $40. I wasn’t sure if it was worth it or not but I decided the bike looked good enough and would be fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Motobecane Restoration</title>
    <link href="http://cycles.rocks/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/"/>
    <id>http://cycles.rocks/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/</id>
    <published>2016-07-10T19:03:30.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-08T03:33:13.772Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/a_side.jpg" alt="Restoration finished" title="Restoration finished">
<p>Back in Feburary while helping my father-in-law repair his shed, I discovered his old Motobecane road bike.  When I first saw it I became a little excited because I thought it might be fun to restore, but he hadn’t ridden it in over 15 years or so and I had never restored anything before.</p>
<p>A few months later I was looking at road bikes for fun at our local bike shops and test rode a few.  That got me excited for a road bike, but I didn’t have the cash. Then I had the bright idea that maybe I could restore my father-in-law’s old Motobecane.  To say the least, it was in really bad shape.</p>
<a id="more"></a> 
<p>So over a few months, I set out to restore it.  The paint was really bad so I thought I’d repaint it, which I don’t recommend doing yourself unless you really know what you are doing (which I don’t).  Unfortunately I didn’t get any good pictures before I started but I took several pictures during the process:</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_shifter3.jpg" alt="Friction shifters" title="Friction shifters">
<p>Friction Shifters</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_shifter1.jpg" alt="Friction shifter up close" title="Friction shifter up close">
<p>Friction shifter up close</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_atom-freewheel1.jpg" alt="Atom Freewheel" title="Atom Freewheel">
<p>I had to purchase a special freewheel hub removal tool to get this off.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_atom-freewheel2.jpg" alt="Atom Freewheel up close" title="Atom Freewheel up close">
<p>I rebuilt the freewheel and replaced all the bearings. Keeping track of the tiny bearings can be difficult.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_bottom-bracket-bearings.jpg" alt="Bottom bracket bearings" title="Bottom bracket bearings">
<p>I replaced the bottom bracket bearings. I couldn’t get the fixed cup off the bottom bracket and busted a 5/8” bolt trying to remove it using the method I found on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Oa8ztfXcHkg" target="_blank" rel="external">Youtube</a>!  I ended up doing my best to clean it without removing it.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_bolt.jpg" alt="busted bolt" title="busted bolt">
<p>My wife wasn’t thrilled helping out after I smashed her toe with the wrench.  She held the bike (I still don’t have a bike stand) while I turned the bolt with the huge adjustable wrench. The bolt busted and wrench came down and brused my wife’s toes and ankle.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_brake1.jpg" alt="Brake before cleaning" title="Brake before cleaning">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_brake2.jpg" alt="Brake before cleaning" title="Brake before cleaning">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_brake3.jpg" alt="Brake after cleaning" title="Brake after cleaning">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_brake4.jpg" alt="Brake after cleaning" title="Brake after cleaning">
<p>I used Evapo-Rust to remove the rust from a lot of parts.  It worked well and is safe to use, however it is kind of expensive.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_front-derailluer.jpg" alt="Simplex front derailluer" title="Simplex front derailluer">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_front-derailluer2.jpg" alt="Simplex front derailluer" title="Simplex front derailluer">
<p>This was very cheap simplex front derailluer.  However, since I didn’t have a lot of money to spend, I ended up using lots of cleaner and a hammer to un-seize it. That was after soaking it in the Evapo-Rust for 12+ hours.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_headset.jpg" alt="Headset and bearings" title="Headset and bearings">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_headset2.jpg" alt="Headset and fork" title="Headset and fork">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_headset3.jpg" alt="Headset bearings" title="Headset bearings">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_headset4.jpg" alt="Headset frame" title="Headset frame">
<p>I replaced all the headset bearings. I probably could have reused them but I bought a bunch of different sizes on Amazon.com.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_hub1.jpg" alt="Wheel hub" title="Wheel hub">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_hub2.jpg" alt="Wheel hub after cleaning outside" title="Wheel hub after cleaning outside">
<p>I replaced all the bearings in the hubs.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_rim.jpg" alt="Rusty rim" title="Rusty rim">
<p>The rims were very rusty.  I used wire wheel on my drill to remove the rust on these. Not sure if that was a smart idea but I didn’t have enough solution to soak them.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/b_paint.jpg" alt="Metallic silver paint job" title="Metallic silver paint job">
<p>I ended up hanging the frame up by rope while I painted it with spray paint.  First I primed it, then painted it silver, then finished off with a clear.  I didn’t do a very good job, but I tried.  It does look better than when I first started though.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/a_derailluer.jpg" alt="Tourney derailluer" title="Tourney derailluer">
<p>I ended up replacing the rear derailluer, it was a cheap Simplex derailluer and had some broken pulleys. It was cheaper to buy the Tourney derailluer than to buy new pulleys.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/a_crank.jpg" alt="Crank" title="Crank">
<p>The pedals were bent badly and didn’t spin well so I chucked them and used some plastic pedals I had lying around.  The crank itself turned out nice, and I didn’t even have to replace the cotter pins!  I recently got another bike off of Craigslist where the pins didn’t come out without a vice so I was surprised I didn’t have any trouble with these pins.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/a_front_close.jpg" alt="Front close view" title="Front close view">
<p>I purchased new tires, tubes, cables, and cable housing.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/a_handlebars.jpg" alt="Handlebars with new tape" title="Handlebars with new tape">
<p>New handlebar tape.  Youtube was a huge help on learning how to properly wrap these old 10 speed bikes.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/a_angle.jpg" alt="front angle view" title="front angle view">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/a_back_angle.jpg" alt="back angle view" title="back angle view">
<img src="/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/a_front.jpg" alt="front view" title="front view">
<p>I learned a lot from this project.  My father-in-law was very surprised.  I ended up giving it back to him for fathers day so he didn’t know I was doing anything to his old bike.</p>
<p>I’m looking forward to my next project.  It’s a <a href="http://www.sheldonbrown.com/retroraleighs/sprite.html" title="&quot;Raleigh Sprite" target="_blank" rel="external">Raleigh Sprite</a>. </p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;img src=&quot;/2016/07/10/Motobecane-Restoration/a_side.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Restoration finished&quot; title=&quot;Restoration finished&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in Feburary while helping my father-in-law repair his shed, I discovered his old Motobecane road bike.  When I first saw it I became a little excited because I thought it might be fun to restore, but he hadn’t ridden it in over 15 years or so and I had never restored anything before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months later I was looking at road bikes for fun at our local bike shops and test rode a few.  That got me excited for a road bike, but I didn’t have the cash. Then I had the bright idea that maybe I could restore my father-in-law’s old Motobecane.  To say the least, it was in really bad shape.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Bike Restoration" scheme="http://cycles.rocks/categories/Bike-Restoration/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Motobecane" scheme="http://cycles.rocks/tags/Motobecane/"/>
    
      <category term="Restoration" scheme="http://cycles.rocks/tags/Restoration/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>About Me</title>
    <link href="http://cycles.rocks/2016/07/05/about-me/"/>
    <id>http://cycles.rocks/2016/07/05/about-me/</id>
    <published>2016-07-06T03:26:46.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-08T03:33:13.725Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I grew up in a small town, on a farm with a large family. Since I was number 6 of 8 kids in my family, no one ever taught me how to ride a bike.  I can vaguely remember an old silver bicycle that I used to teach myself how to ride. I think it looked something like this:</p>
<img src="/2016/07/05/about-me/firstbike.jpg" alt="My first bike" title="My first bike">
<a id="more"></a> 
<p>When I was old enough, my parents got me a steel Walmart mountain bike that I would ride to my friends house and back. Sadly I don’t have any pictures of it and don’t remember the model or year.  My friend lived in town 3 miles from where I lived, and now I wonder how my parents ever let me ride by myself that far without worrying about me. Times have definitely changed.</p>
<p>When I turned 19, I went on a mission for my church to the Oregon Eugene mission.  It was there that I acquired a <a href="http://www.bicyclebluebook.com/SearchListingDetail.aspx?id=91390&amp;make=679&amp;model=40975" target="_blank" rel="external">2002 Diamondback Topanga</a>. I remember it was newer and shiny and I was excited to ride it!  I rode that bike a lot on my mission. At the close of my mission, I never shipped it home. I couldn’t say why except I was poor and couldn’t spare much money at the time.  So I ended up donating it to the mission for some other poor missionary that would serve after me.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/05/about-me/Aug31-2004030.jpg" alt="This is an example image" title="This is an example image">
<img src="/2016/07/05/about-me/Aug31-2004035.jpg" alt="This is an example image" title="This is an example image">
<p>When I returned home, I was blessed to start a job working for my Dad at a new and thriving electronics recycling warehouse.  That was convenient because computers was my love and I was among so much computer junk I was in heaven. I always had a knack for tinkering around with computers.  I’m sure I drove my parents nuts how many times I had our family computer disassembled growing up.</p>
<p>Not too long after, I started a second job as an IT Specialist intern at a small company called Arkansas Power Electronics International.  I was finally starting to make a little money so I bought a used car and started school in computer science. About a year or so later I bought another bicycle.  This time I bought a <a href="http://www.bicyclebluebook.com/SearchListingDetail.aspx?id=94141&amp;make=737&amp;model=58088" target="_blank" rel="external">2006 Scott Reflex 50</a>.</p>
<img src="/2016/07/05/about-me/bike.jpg" alt="This is an example image" title="This is an example image">
<p>That was the time when everyone in my family was going mountain biking, and there were few paved trails in Fayetteville and the surrounding area, and mountain bike trails were in abundance.</p>
<p>I never really got into cycling to work until several years later after I had gotten married, had two kids, and had incentive to keep some weight off :)  I have a good friend though that kept encouraging my desire get into cycling more and more.</p>
<p>I started riding my bike 5 miles to work every so often, but I was still in school and working full time so time didn’t allow many opportunities. My friend eventually persuaded me to get Nashbar City slicks for my mountain bike. That changed my entire commute!  No more clunky mountain bike tires slowing me down.</p>
<p>I started riding more during the nice part of the seasons, when it wasn’t too cold or too hot.  I bought my wife some city slicks for her mountain bike as well and we would ride the trails in Fayetteville together with our kids.</p>
<p>Eventually, we rode the <a href="http://www.nwatrails.org/trail/razorback-regional-greenway/" target="_blank" rel="external">Razorback Regional Greenway</a> which was about a 40 mile ride, the longest I’ve ridden to date.</p>
<p>The friend I mentioned before has encouraged me to get a road bike so I can keep up with him on rides.  I just couldn’t afford buy an expensive road bike, but I didn’t want to get a cheap one so I kept holding off. Then one day, I was helping out my Father-in-law clean out his shed and I see and old rusty road bike.  I examined it as best I could but didn’t see any hope for it.</p>
<p>A little while later, when I got the bug again for a road bike, and I thought, “What about fixing up my Father-in-laws old road bike?”  So I had my wife pick it up and bring it home.  How bad could it be?  Very.  Rust was everywhere, tires were bad, rear derailleur had broken pulleys, etc… But that didn’t dissuade me.  I stripped the paint and rust, did my own shoddy paint job, re-lubed and greased all parts, replacing parts as needed, and after many many hours of work now I’m hooked!</p>
<img src="/2016/07/05/about-me/20160613_195410.jpg" alt="This is an example image" title="This is an example image">
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;I grew up in a small town, on a farm with a large family. Since I was number 6 of 8 kids in my family, no one ever taught me how to ride a bike.  I can vaguely remember an old silver bicycle that I used to teach myself how to ride. I think it looked something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/2016/07/05/about-me/firstbike.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My first bike&quot; title=&quot;My first bike&quot;&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
